<TEI>
	<teiHeader></teiHeader>
<text>
<front>

	<titlePage>
	<p>Price 1d. Post-free 2d.[underlined]</p>
	<docTitle>A Letter from 
		<persName>LORD ALFRED DOUGLAS</persName> on 
		<persName>ANDRE GIDE</persName>'S Lies about Himself and
		<persName>OSCAR WILDE</persName>
	</docTitle>
	<byline>Set forth with comments by
		<docAuthor><persName>Robert Harborough Sherard</persName></docAuthor>(Knight of the Legion of Honour)
	</byline>
	<docImprint>Issued by
		<publisher>The [Vindex bold] Publishing Co.</publisher>,
		<pubPlace>CALVI</pubPlace>
		<pubPlace>(Corsica)</pubPlace>
	</docImprint>
	<docDate>1933</docDate>
</titlePage>
</front>

<body>

<pb n="[1]"/>
	
	<head>LORD ALFRED DOUGLAS<lb/> on ANDRE GIDE</head>

		<p>A distressing feature of the ill-advised publication by Peter
			Davies Ltd., in Dr G. J. Renier's life of OSCAR WILDE, of
the scandalous and lying story about the deceased poet and playwright
which appears in Andr[e] Gide's pornographical and therefore widely
read autobiography, <title>Si le grain ne meurt</title>, is that by directing atten-</lb>
tion to this obscene compilation it constitutes an even worse attack</lb>
on that distinguished scholar and master-poet, Lord Alfred Douglas,</lb>
who is still living and whom Gide attacks with even more mendacity and malice.</p></lb>
<p>In the following letter to the author of the pamphlet entitled :</lb>
<hi rend="italic"><title>ANDR[E] GIDE'S LIES</title></hi> (publication of which by <hi rend="italic">The Vindex Publi-</lb>
shing Co</hi>, of Calvi, is being held up <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">pendente lite</foreign></hi>) Lord Alfred</lb>
Douglas sums up his opinion on Gide an his book and explains</lb>
why he has taken no action in connection with the atrocious libels</lb>
which it contains about him and Oscar Wilde.</p></lb>

<div type="letter">
<hi rend-"italic">
Hove 1363 35, Forth Avenue,
Hove, Sussex.

May 25, 1933.
Dear Sherard,

<p>Andr[e] Gide's seory about Oscar and myself in <hi rend="plain">Si le grain
ne meurt</hi> is a mass of lies and misrepresentations. When I first
read the book (long after it was written) I hesitated what action
to take about it, because I knew that a libel action in France
would be a farce. As you know, there is nothing in France
which corresponds to our own laws of libel. In England, a man
who is libelled can get thousands of pounds in damages, or he
can get the libeller sent to prison. In France, the libeller is condemned
in the <hi rend="plain"><foreign sml:lang="fr">Police Correctionnelle</foreign></hi> to some paltry fine, probably
200 francs! If Gide had been an Englishman, I could have
taken criminal proceedings against him and he would certainly
have been sent to prison, probably for the maximum two years.</p>

<p>As you say, if I had gone to Paris and blown his brains
out, no jury in the world (least of all a French jury) would
have convicted me. But being a Catholic, it was not possible for
me even to think of doing this. So on the whole, after much
consideration, I decided to do nothing and to refrain from stir-
ing up the mud or advertising Gide's filthy book</p>

</pb>
<page number=[2]>

<p>I had several years of fighting against Ross, Harris and
others, involving frightful mental strain and a ruinous expen-
diture, and I felt that I simply had neither the means nor the
energy to start a new campaign in a foreign country. So I
contented myself with writing my Autobiography and leaving
the literary world to judge me by my own written words. Gide's
confessions about his own disgusting conduct and the whole
record of this dull, fifth-rate writer (this "egoist without an ego"
as Oscar called him) whose success among the stupid and corrupt
people depends entirely on his revolting pornography, are, I
believe, quite sufficient to discredit his contempible lies about
two poets.</p>
 
  



</body>
</text>
</TEI>


